Guide to the Kate Millett papers, 1912-2002, bulk 1951-2001 RL.10070
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kate Millett papers
1912-2002, bulk 1951-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Millett, Kate
RL.10070
93 Linear Feet 198 boxes; 29 oversize folders
The Kate Millett papers document Millett's life and activities as feminist writer, theorist, and artist, teacher, and global activist, based in New York City. They also document the 20th century women's movement, feminist theory, as well as feminism and women's rights around the globe, especially in France, Italy, and the Middle East. There are many files of correspondence with family, partners, friends, writers, artists, and activists, including significant exchanges with Rita Mae Brown, Phyllis Chesler, Alix Kates Shulman, Yoko Ono, and Gloria Steinem. Annotated manuscripts and other items related to her major publications are present. Topics in these works include prison systems; mental institutions; psychiatry, medications, and mental health; torture and imprisonment; politics, gender, and sexuality; and mother/daughter relationships. Subject files contain research on these topics, as well as materials on abortion, feminism, organizations, the arts, gay rights, and Millett's diagnosis of bipolar disorder, involuntary clinical treatments, and subsequent involvement in anti-psychiatry activism. Additional series relate to writings by other authors; Millett's work as a visual artist and her New York State artists' colony; and her student years and teaching. Other formats in the collection include electronic records, chiely writings; many recordings of interviews, lectures, speeches, art openings, and conversations; photographs; artwork, including drawings, sculptures, and installation components; and print materials such as articles, cards, clippings, fliers, magazine issues, and posters. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture at Duke University.
Biographical Note
1934 Sept. 14 Born in St. Paul, Minn. to Helen Feely and James A. Millett
1952-1956 B.A., University of Minnesota
1956-1958 B.A., first-class honors, St. Hilda's College, Oxford University
1958 Instructor in English, University of North Carolina at Greensboro
1961-1963 Instructor in English Literature, Waseda University, Tokyo
1963 First sculpture show, Minami Gallery, Tokyo
1964-1969 Instructor in English Literature, Barnard College
1965 Married Fumio Yoshimura
1965-1968 Chair of Education Committee, National Organization for Women
1970 Professor, Bryn Mawr College Publication of Sexual Politics Ph.D., Columbia University
1971 Publication of Three Lives
1973 Distinguished Visiting Professor, California State University at Sacramento Publication of Prostitution Papers
1974 Publication of Flying
1977 Publication of Sita
1978 Founded women's art colony and farm in Poughkeepsie, N.Y.
1979 Publication of The Basement, and Going to Iran, with photography by Sophie Keir
1982 Publication of Going to Iran
1985 Divorced from Fumio Yoshimura
1990 Publication of The Loony-bin Trip
1994 Publication of The Politics of Cruelty
1995 Publication of A.D.
1998 Adjunct Professor, New York University
2001 Publication of Mother Millett
2004 Evicted from her apartment at 295 Bowery after a prolonged court battle; the building was demolished as part of a redevelopment plan
2012 The art colony founded by Millett became a non-profit, and changed its name to Millett Center for the Arts
2013 Inducted into the National Women's Hall of Fame, Seneca Falls, N.Y.
2017 Sept. 6 Died in Paris
Conditions Governing Access
Correspondence to and from Sophie Keir is closed for her lifetime.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Many items have been reformatted, and digital access copies are available. Some items however may require the creation of access copies.
Although these recordings are now stored in climate-controlled conditions, the playback and sound quality for original items that have not been digitized is unknown.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library to request access before coming to use these materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Large-format items from the Elegy for Sita subseries of the Artwork grouping are restricted and require approval by curatorial staff before use: "Ink drawing" (AW10), and "Photos of Sita" (AW11). Large three-dimensional pieces may also require permission for viewing.
These oversized items should be unpacked in a staff workroom with curatorial or conservation assistance before being checked out to the reading room. Staff will contact Conservation for unpacking or repacking assistance if needed.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic records have been migrated to a library server and are available only in the Rubenstein Library onsite reading room.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Kate Millett Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases and gifts from 2000-2017.
Related Materials
For related archival collections, see the Phyllis Chesler Papers, Merle Hoffman Papers, Robin Morgan Papers, and Alix Kates Shulman Papers, all located in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Collection Overview
The papers of Kate Millett provide rich documentation of Millett's activities as a feminist activist, artist, and author of numerous works, including Sexual Politics, whose publication established her as one of the founding 20th century feminists. Other works for which supporting materials exist are The Loony-bin Trip, Flying, and The Basement.
Seen in a broader context, Millett's papers provide important documentation of the history of the feminist movement and feminist theory in the United States, including the history of the National Organization for Women. Materials in the collection also cover feminism and the social conditions for women around the globe, especially in France, Italy, and the Middle East - most notably Iran, where Millett traveled in 1979-1980.
The earliest dates in the collection, 1912 and 1928, refer respectively to an early family photograph, and historical resources used when writing the book A.D.. The bulk of the materials span her adult life from the 1950s through the early 2000s.
The collection content reflects the intensely personal nature of much of Millett's work and the frequent fusion of her personal, political, and professional interests, strongly evident in the many files of personal and literary correspondence, including significant exchanges with Ti-Grace Atkinson, Rita Mae Brown, Phyllis Chesler, Andrea Dworkin, Cynthia McAdams, Yoko Ono, Alix Kates Shulman, Gloria Steinem, and many other activists, writers, artists, friends, partners, and family.
Additional series include writings by other authors; papers documenting Millett's work as an artist and instructor; files relating to her New York State farm and artists' colony; materials from Millett's student years, including her thesis which led to the book, Sexual Politics; and scripts and other papers relating to Millett's little-known documentary film, Three Lives (a copy of the film also exists in the collection). Other materials document her relationship with her mother during the last years of her mother's life, also the topic of her book, Mother Millett. Subject files relate to Millett's involvement with the gay and lesbian communities, her research on prisons and torture, and her diagnosis with bipolar disorder and subsequent involvement in anti-psychiatry activism. There are also extensive printed materials such as serial issues, articles, clippings, posters, fliers, mainstream and grassroots newsletters, event programs, and manifestos.
Audiovisual materials, many available through digital access copies, include audio and video recordings of Millett's lectures, speeches, and many conversations with activists, friends, and family. There are also many photographs, slides, and negatives documenting Millett's activities and the people in her life.
Rounding out the visual components of the collection are over 250 pieces of Millett's artwork created by Millett, who was also involved in the Fluxus art movement. Predominant formats include ink drawings, calligraphy, and graphic prints. There are also sculptures and other three-dimensional works, some of which formed part of an installation representing events that surrounded the murder of Sylvia Likens, also the subject of Millett's book, The Basement. A full inventory of the artwork is available in this collection guide.
Electronic formats include some correspondence, book drafts, and other writings. These files are included in the inventory under the appropriate series. The electronic files have been migrated to a library server; please contact the Rubenstein Library for access.
Antipsychiatry; Artist colonies -- United States; Feminism -- France; Feminism -- Italy; Feminism -- Middle East; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Feminism -- United States; Feminism and art; Feminism and literature; Feminists -- United States -- Correspondence; Feminist theory -- United States -- 20th century; Gay rights -- United States; Lesbians -- United States; Mentally ill -- Commitment and detention -- United States; Mothers and daughters; Prisons -- United States; Psychiatric hospitals -- United States; Torture; Women artists -- United States; Women -- Mental health; Iran -- Social conditions; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- 1951-; Audiocassettes; Drawings (visual works); Electronic records; Sculpture (visual work); Videocassettes; Photographs; Negatives (photographs); Slides (photographs); Brown, Rita Mae; Chesler, Phyllis; Dworkin, Andrea; MacAdams, Cynthia, 1939-; Atkinson, Ti-Grace; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Shulman, Alix Kates; Steinem, Gloria; Millett, Kate; National Organization for Women; Ono, Yoko
- Correspondence, 1958-2002; 1; 8 Linear Feet 16 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Correspondence to and from Sophie Keir is closed to use for her lifetime.
  Scope and Contents
  The Kate Millett correspondence series is organized into two subgroups: letters regarding Millett's literary works and activism (1970-2002); and letters of a more personal nature (1958-1999). It should be said, however, that there is considerable overlap between the two. Each group contains both outgoing and incoming letters, but the majority are letters sent to Millett.
  Both subgroups are organized in the following sequence: alphabetically by correspondent's last name, alphabetically by topical folder title, and folders of correspondence arranged by date.
  In addition to letters, other forms of correspondence include postcards and greeting cards. Sometimes there are sketches and photographs enclosed.
  Significant correspondents in this series include: Rita Mae Brown, Phyllis Chesler, Maria del Drogo, Andrea Dworkin, Yoko Ono, Alix Kates Shulman, Gloria Steinem, Fumio Yoshimura (Millett's husband), and Millett family members, especially Millett's mother and sister. Correspondence to and from Sophie Keir, Millett's surviving spouse, are closed to use for her lifetime.
  Folder titles are transcribed from the original titles when present.
  - Literary Correspondence, 1966-2002 and undated; 1.1
    The literary letters group speaks to Millett's work as a feminist writer and activist, and includes many pieces of correspondence with Rita Mae Brown, Phyllis Chesler, Cynthia McAdams, Alix Kates Shulman, and Gloria Steinem. There are also a few letters from Yoko Ono, Pauli Murray, Toni Morrison and several from her husband, Fumio Yoshimura, about Millett's artists' colony (the Farm), her writings, and activism.
    Of note are the many folders of fan mail for her major works, particularly Flying. There are also many items related to book sales and speaking requests.
    The last sequence of folders is organized by date, and contains letters from numerous people and fans about Millett's literary works.
    - Ballantine, 1975-1977 (Box C1)
    - Simone de Beauvoir correspondence and conference, 1980-1984, 1987, and undated (Box C1)
    - Rita Mae Brown, 1972-1973; 1976-1978; 1984 (Box C1)
    - Phyllis Chesler, 1973-1978; 1985-1998; undated (Box C1)
    - Sarah Douglas and The Lavender Network, 1993 (Box C1)
    - Andrea Dworkin, 1975-1992; undated (Box C1)
    - Anne Elliott, 1981; undated (Box C1)
    - Linda Griffith, 1974-1975; undated (Box C1)
    - Kmopf and Borchardt, 1973-1974; 1976 (Box C1)
    - Ron Liefer, 1990 May 13 (Box C1)
    - Catherine Mackinnon, 1985 October 31 (Box C1)
    - Norman Mailer, 1974 (Box C1)
    - Tatyana Mamonova, 1988-1993 (Box C1)
    - Kathleen Marcato, 1979-1982; undated (Box C1)
    - Pauli Murray, 1970 July 31 (Box C1)
    - Yoko Ono, 1966; 1972-1974; 1994; undated (Box C1)
    - Mary Bess Ross, 1982-1985; 1992; undated (Box C1)
    - Hannelore Schroder, 1981; 1984 (Box C1)
    - Alice Schwartzer (On The Politics of Cruelty), 1985-1992, and undated; (2 folders) (Box C1)
    - Delphine Seyrig ("Delphine Listens"), 1987-1992; undated (Box C1)
    - Lisa Sherman correspondence and Millett's article, 1975-1976; undated (Box C1)
    - Alix Kates Shulman, 1973-1974; 1997-1999; undated (Box C2)
    - Gloria Steinem, 1976; 1992; 1998; undated (Box C2)
    - Marina Urbach, 1979-1981; undated (Box C2)
    - Fumio Yoshimura, 1978-1987; 1992; undated (Box C2)
    - The Basement - Fan mail, 1979-1984 (Box C2)
    - Book catalog, 1990 (Box C2)
    - Book requests - direct sales, 1981-1987; undated (Box C2)
    - Book requests - direct sales, 1985-1986; undated (Box C2)
    - "Children and Sexuality" article and Carol Vance correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box C2)
    - "Crazy Comrades (Men)", 1990-1991 (Box C2)
    - "Crazy Comrades (Women)", 1990-1991; undated (Box C2)
    - England, 1976; 1979; 1991-1992 (Box C2)
    - Fans, 1984-1991; undated (Box C2)
    - Fans, 1993 (Box C2)
    - Fans, 1994- January 1995 (Box C2)
    - Flying fan mail, 1975; undated; (4 folders) (Box C3)
    - Fans - Barbara Francis, 1992-1993; undated (Box C3)
    - Farm, 1992- January 1993; undated; (2 folders) (Box C3)
    - Flying - unopened mail, 1976 (Box C3)
    - Form letter for book requests, undated (Box C3)
    - Friends, 1978; undated (Box C3)
    - Musician, 1977 April (Box C3)
    - "Occasional Piece - Nouvelle Observateur [sic] - Engaged Literature", 1982; undated (Box C3)
    - The Politics of Cruelty - publishers' correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box C3)
    - Poster requests - direct sales, 1981 (Box C3)
    - Poster requests - direct sales, 1981-1985; undated (Box C3)
    - Reprints, 1997-1998 (Box C4)
    - Secretarial work - Bonny, 1973; undated; (3 folders) (Box C4)
    - Secretarial work - Mallory, 1970; undated (Box C4)
    - Speaking engagements, 1974-1975; undated (Box C4)
    - Token Learning, 1968-1972; undated (Box C4)
    - "Work about my work", 1984-1985 (Box C4)
    - Work letters, 1970-1971; undated (Box C4)
    - Writers, 1975-1981; 1986 (Box C4)
    - Bici Forbes (for Kate Millett) letters, 1971 (Box C4)
    - 1972 (Box C4)
    - January 1973 - June 1973 (Box C4)
    - July 1973 - December 1973 (Box C5)
    - 1974-1978 (Box C5)
    - 1979-1981 (Box C5)
    - December 1982 (Box C5)
    - 1983 (Box C5)
    - 1984 (Box C5)
    - 1985, undated (Box C5)
    - 1986-1988 (Box C5)
    - 1989, undated (Box C5)
    - January 1990 - June 1990 (Box C5)
    - July 1990 - December 1990 (Box C5)
    - January 1991 - April 1991 (Box C5)
    - 1991 April - 1991 May (Box C6)
    - September 1991 - December 1991 (Box C6)
    - July 1992 - December 1992 (Box C6)
    - January 1993 - June 1993 (Box C6)
    - July 1993 - December 1993 (Box C6)
    - January 1994 - June 1994 (Box C6)
    - July 1994 - December 1994 (Box C6)
    - 1995 - January 1996 (Box C6)
    - 1997, undated (Box C7)
    - January 1998 - April 1998 (Box C7)
    - May 1998 - August 1998 (Box C7)
    - September 1998 - December 1998 (Box C7)
    - May 1999 - August 1999 (Box C7)
    - January 1999 - April 1999, (2 folders) (Box C7)
    - September 1999 - December 1999 (Box C7)
    - 2000-2001, undated (Box C7)
    - January 2002 - June 2002 (Box C8)
    - July 2002 - December 2002 (Box C8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1958-1999 and undated; 1.2
    The personal letters cover a wide range of topics, including Millett's involuntary commitment to psychiatric wards, the development of her sexual identity, her experiences teaching at several academic institutions, and her personal relationships with friends and family. Folder titles are transcribed from the original titles when present.
    The letters from Millett's family include her mother, two sisters, her husband, Fumio Yoshimura, her partner, Maria del Drogo, and spouse Sophie Keir, who was by Millett's side at her death in 2017. The letters to and from Sophie Keir are restricted to use for her lifetime.
    As in the first group, there is a sequence of folders organized by date rather than name; it contains personal letters from numerous friends and family members on various topics.
    Correspondence to and from Sophie Keir is closed for her lifetime.
    - Z. Budapest, 1973-1990; undated (Box C8)
    - Clarkie [Linda Clarke], 1971-1990; undated (Box C8)
    - Marie Deyoc, 1990; undated (Box C8)
    - Alex de Lallier, 1979-1983; undated (Box C8)
    - Helen Millett on Sita, 1977 (Box C8)
    - Helen Millett on Looney Bin Trio, 1985 (Box C8)
    - Mother and Mallory, 1967-1974; undated (Box C8)
    - Mother and Mallory, 1975-1979; undated (Box C8)
    - Mother and Mallory, 1980-1988; 1991; undated (Box C8)
    - Sister Peg, 1986-1998; undated (Box C8)
    - Liz Petrulio and Jean Sherman, 1961 (Box C8)
    - Liz Petrulio and Jean Sherman, 1962 (Box C8)
    - Liz Petrulio and Jean Sherman, 1963 (Box C9)
    - Liz Petrulio, 1976-1999; undated (Box C9)
    - Sally Millett Rau, 1973-1985; undated (Box C9)
    - Jean Sherman, 1970; 1973; 1977-1978; 1988; undated (Box C9)
    - Milly [Mildred Thompson], 1975-1987; undated; (3 folders) (Box C9)
    - Janey Washburn and CP, 1976-1985; undated (Box C9)
    - Fumio Yoshimura, 1962-1963; 1970-1973; undated (Box C9)
    - Fumio Yoshimura, 1974; undated (Box C9)
    - Barnard, 1967-1986; (2 folders) (Box C9)
    - Campaign for Michael X. Malik, 1973-1974; undated (Box C9)
    - "Communist Party" Thanksgiving, 1991; undated (Box C9)
    - "Communist Party" Thanksgiving, 1997-1998 (Box C9)
    - Family, 1969-1970; 1973-1975; undated (Box C9)
    - Family, 1982-1988; undated (Box C10)
    - Family, 1993-1998 (Box C10)
    - Family, 1994; undated (Box C10)
    - French sisters, 1974-1975; undated (Box C10)
    - Friends' congratulations, 1970-1971; undated; (2 folders) (Box C10)
    - Job search correspondence and notes, 1963; undated (Box C10)
    - "Kate's class - Berkeley", 1975-1982; (2 folders) (Box C10)
    - Paris, 1978-1986 (Box C10)
    - Psychiatric Survivors' Movement, 1987-1997; (2 folders) (Box C10)
    - Psychiatric Survivors' Movement - information request ("Lifeline"), 1990-1991; undated (Box C10)
    - Sacramento, 1973; undated (Box C11)
    - Sacramento State University, 1972-1973; undated (Box C11)
    - Sacramento State University - the press, 1973-1974; undated (Box C11)
    - St. Paul, 1974-1985; undated (Box C11)
    - "Unanswered mail etc.", September 1958 - January 1959 (Box C11)
    - "Unanswered mail", 1964 (Box C11)
    - "Weird Sisters/ Mad Women Circle", 1989-1992; undated (Box C11)
    - Women's Music Festival, 1973 and undated; (2 folders) (Box C11)
    - Women's Music Festival form letters, 1973 (Box C11)
    - 1960-1961 (Box C11)
    - 1962 (Box C11)
    - 1963, undated (Box C11)
    - 1967-1969 (Box C11)
    - 1966-1967 (Box C12)
    - Notes, 1967-1969 (Box C12)
    - 1968 (Box C12)
    - January 1969 - June 1969 (Box C12)
    - July 1969 - December 1969 (Box C12)
    - 1970, undated (Box C12)
    - 1970-1973 (Box C12)
    - 1971 (Box C12)
    - 1971-1975 (Box C12)
    - 1972 (Box C12)
    - 1973, undated (Box C12)
    - Unopened mail, 1973 (Box C12)
    - January 1974 - June 1974 (Box C12)
    - July 1974 - December 1974 (Box C13)
    - Unopened mail, 1975 (Box C13)
    - January 1976 - June 1976 (Box C13)
    - July 1976 - September 1976 (Box C13)
    - October 1976 - December 1976 (Box C13)
    - 1975, undated (Box C13)
    - Unopened mail, 1976 (Box C13)
    - 1976, undated (Box C13)
    - 1978, undated (Box C13)
    - 1979 (Box C13)
    - 1986-1989, undated (Box C13)
    - 1980-1985, undated (Box C13)
    - 1990-1991, undated (Box C14)
    - 1992-1993 (Box C14)
    - 1994-1995 (Box C14)
    - 1996-1997 (Box C14)
    - Undated correspondence (Box C14)
    - 1998-1999, undated (Box C14)
    - Gloria Allen, 1980-1983 (Box C14)
    - Anne, undated (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita], July 1972 - August 1973 (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita], September 1973 - December 1973 (Box C14)
    - Notes - Maria del Drago [Sita], 1973? (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita], 1973; undated (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita], 1974-1976; undated; (2 folders) (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita] (1 of 2), 1975-1978; undated (Box C14)
    - Maria del Drago [Sita] (2 of 2), 1975-1978; undated (Box C15)
    - "Trio" [Jennifer Floryan], 1989-1994; undated (Box C15)
    - Cynthia MacAdams, 1976-1986; 1992-1999; undated (Box C15)
    - Millett notes, 1974? (Box C15)
    - Ann Pollon, 1974-1975; undated (Box C15)
    - Collette Shammah, 1976-1978; 1980; 1995; 1997; undated (Box C15)
    - Sophie Keir, 1978-19991 and undated; (3 folders) (Box C16)
- Writings and Speeches, 1928-2001, bulk 1968-1998; 42 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains written and typed drafts, research notes, correspondence, proofs and galleys, electronic records, and other materials related to Millett's publications, speeches, and interviews. Works by other authors can be found in the Writings by Others subseries at the end of this series, arranged by author name.
  Materials on Sexual Politics, Flying, Sita, The Basement, The Loony-bin Trip, The Politics of Cruelty, and Mother Millett are located in individual subseries. Less extensive material on Millett's other published books can be found at the beginning of the Other Writings Subseries.
  Millett's own folder titles have been retained when possible. For each book title, undated drafts and notes come first, followed by book reviews, fan mail, contracts, and material collected by Millett as background for the book. Book drafts are sometimes labeled by letter, as in "draft A" or "draft B." This does not imply that one was written before the other, but only gives an order to their presentation.
  The Other Writings subseries offers material related to Millett's articles and unpublished manuscripts. The Interviews subseries contains correspondence, clippings, and a small number of transcripts of interviews with Millett. The Speeches subseries includes notes and drafts, along with related records, while the Engagements subseries primarily consists of correspondence about speaking engagements, and materials from conferences in which Millett participated. Subseries files are in chronological order.
  The series includes some documents in electronic format. In general, electronic documents are grouped with corresponding from which diskettes were taken from, or folders containing related paper documents. If there is no corresponding folder, the documents are marked "electronic format only." Electronic versions of book drafts are in chronological order together with other dated material. For each electronic document, the container entry provides the file name, the date the file was last modified, and the number assigned to the original computer disk on which the file was received. Please contact the Rubenstein Library to request access to electronic records.